Khawaja Abaid Ullah

Machine Learner

khawaja.abaid@gmail.com

+923095868628

in KhawajaAbaid

khawajaabaid.github.io

Computer Science graduate specializing in data science and machine learning (through self-learning). I love building niche and fun projects with the focus on creating value for others, and for self-learning.

My long-term goals are to democratize Artificial Intelligence and make it safer for environment.

SKILLS_

Programming: Python, JavaScript, C++, C#

Data Wrangling: Pandas, Numpy, Scipy, Statsmodels, NetworkX

Matoplotlib, Seaborn Visualization:

Scikit-Learn, XGBoost, CatBoost, LightGBM, Keras/Tensorflow Machine Learning:

NLP: AllenNLP, NLTK, Spacy, Hugging Face

Database: SQL, MongoDB

Cloud: AWS EC2, AWS SageMaker, Google Colab, Kaggle Notebooks

Web Scraping: Requests, Beautiful Soup, Selenium, Scrapy

Others: Django, PyQt5, Git, OpenCV, Photoshop, MS Office

EDUCATION.

University of Narowal

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science (GPA: **3.69**/4.0) 2017-2021

Punjab Group of Colleges, Pasrur

FSc. Pre-Engineering (81.72% Marks) 2015-2017

Educational Testing Service

Test of English as a Foreign Language (TOEFL): 110/120 Marks Sep, 2021

Educational Testing Service

GRE General Test: (318/340) Marks April, 2022

CERTIFICATES_

Harvard University's CS 50

CS50x 2022 Intro to Computer Science (Official Certificate Link)

EXPERIENCE_

Junior Python Developer (Remote) / Comundo, Denmark

Feb 2023 – Present

- Developing semi-supervised, robust web scrapers for data curation
- Aggregating the scraped data to store in database

Open-Source Developer / Self Employed

Mar 2021 - Present

- Prewordict: An NLP based nerdy game. (https://khawajaabaid.github.io/prewordict/)
- TweetsCloudBot: A twitter bot that generates word clouds of tweets. (Bot Twitter Link)
- eBookEZ: A desktop application that finds meanings and synonyms of English words. (Github)

Freelance Software Developer / Fiverr

Oct 2021 - Present

Web Scraping, Automation, GUI-based desktop apps development.

Crowd Detection and Behavior Analysis / Final Year Project, BS-CS

- Worked on Computer Vision to train Deep Learning models for Person Detection as well as Detection of Certain (similarly attired) Groups among crowd.
- Developed custom algorithms for Chaos Detection and Crowd Detection

USED: TensorFlow Object Detection API, OpenCV, Matplotlib, PyQt5, Google Colab

Gamer Assistant / Addresses the unaddressed needs of gamers

- A website based on Django and consisting of three main components as highlighted below.
- FPS Predictor v2: Predicts the expected FPS for a user specified PC for a specified game
 - o Scraped and curated FPS and games data from sites like Steam & Techpowerup.
 - Used XGBoost to build the FPS Predictor
- Games Recommender: Recommends games based on user's specified PC
- PC Recommender: Recommends PC components based on user's favorite games

USED: Django, XGBoost, Pandas, Scikit-Learn, Beautiful Soup, Requests

Video Games FPS Predictor v1

- Scraped games info and their FPS data from the internet (Steam and other sites)
- Used Random Forest algorithm to build the FPS predictor

USED: Scikit-Learn, Pandas, Requests, Beautiful Soup

Prewordict / A fun little nerdy game (Inspired by Wordle)

- Processed 180,000 medium articles and clustered the similar words
- Generated word clouds from these clusters. Given a word cloud, user has to predict one word that best belongs in the word cloud.

USED: Scikit-Learn (TFIDF, SVD, KMeans), WordCloud, Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib, Kaggle

HONORS, AWARDS _____

Topper Computer Science Class of 2021 / University of Narowal

July 2021

KAGGLE COMPETITIONS ————

•	3rd Place Heart Disease Prediction Competition / <u>Kaggle</u>	June 2022
•	Placed 50 th /665: Tabular Playground S03 E03 - Jan 2023 / Kaggle	Jan 2023
•	Placed 206 th /693: Tabular Playground S03 E01 - Jan 2023 / Kaggle	Jan 2023
•	Placed 284th /770: Tabular Playground S03 E02 - Jan 2023 / Kaggle	Jan 2023

ACTIVITIES_

I'm always in the pursuit of learning. I participate in Kaggle Competitions. I love books, coding, gaming, F1 and jogging.